## Maria Fernanda Ibarra Gutiérrez

CURP: IAGF890825MDFBTR07
Nationality: Mexican

Birth Date: 25 August 1989

Sex: Female Civil State: Single

E-mail: fernanda.ibarraop@gmail.com



Statistical analysis of data has interested me for the whole of my career. Moreover, I have experience with collected and systematized information through tools programming. I have a particular interest in the analysis of information and implementation of mathematical models to explain social, demographic and risk phenomena.

Values Honesty Responsibility Leadership Other interest Reading

## **Education and qualifications**

### National Autonomous University of Mexico (UNAM) 2009-2013

Science Faculty.

Bachelor's degree in Actuarial Science.

Modules included a deep background of mathematical and statistical modelling.

#### Courses.

**2019** – Summer School on Multidimensional Poverty Analysis by Oxford Poverty and Human Development Initiative (OPHI) University of Oxford

2018 - Multivariate Methods by the Mathematics Research Centre, S.C.

2018 - Crime Victimization Surveys by UNODC.

2018 - How to read and process gender data using R? By Civic Data.

2018 - Record Linkage Workshop by the Mathematics Research Centre, S.C.

**2017** - Online Certified Introduction to Feminist Theory and Research by the National Autonomous University of Mexico.

**2016** - Colloquium on Feminist and Gender Studies (Women and Violence: Intersectionality) by the University of Brasilia.

**2016** - Certified in Probability and Statistics from the National Autonomous University of Mexico.

2015 - Certified in Statistics by Actuary Hunter.

2015 - Certified in Applications of Data Mining by the Technological Institute and Higher Education of Monterrey.

2014 - Course on Statistics in R by Applied Mathematics and Actuary Training.

**2014** - Seminar on Classical Foundations of Feminist Thought 1 by Construction and Gender Analysis Research and Teaching Centre S.C.

2013 - Certified in Human Rights by the Human Rights Centre "Fray Francisco de Vittoria".

**2013** - Intensive Workshop in Mathematical Models Applied to Research in Social Sciences with Special Orientation to Political Science by the National Autonomous University of Mexico.

2013 - Course of Operational Risk Management 2 by NUMERAVI Risk valuation and analysis S.C.

2012 - Course of Operational Risk Management 1 by NUMERAVI Risk valuation and analysis S.C.

#### Computational qualifications.

R: advanced level. STATA: basic level SPSS: medium level.

Tableau: Visualizations, basic level.

SAS: basic level. MySQL: medium level.

Visual Fox Pro: medium level, knowledge of programming language in Fox Pro 9.0.

#### Languages.

International English Language Testing System (IELTS) 6.5 Certification of English Language for Foreigners TOEFL (paper based) 563. Certification of Portuguese Language for Foreigners CELPE.

## **Employment experience**

INSTITUTE OF RESEARCH ON SUSTAINABLE DEVELOPMENT AND SOCIAL EQUITY OF THE

#### **Quantitative Research Assistant**

 Support the theoretical and methodological construction of the multidimensional measurement of urban poverty.

# IBEROAMERICAN UNIVERSITY (EQUIDE) Present

NATIONAL INSTITUTE OF STATISTIC AND GEOGRAPHY (INEGI) 05/01/2017 to 05/31/2018 General Directorate of Government, Public Safety and Justice Statistics

BANK OF MEXICO 07/09/2013 to 06/30/2016 General Directorate of Emission

BANK OF MEXICO 10/30/2012 to 4/30/2013 General Directorate of Emission

- Cleaning and processing databases.
- Statistical analysis.

## Link of Methodological Support.

- Generation of databases based on INEGI censuses and surveys.
- Generation and validation of indicators related to public safety, gender, violence, poverty, corruption, among others.
- Generation of visualizations based on the indicators.
- Methodological support for documents and presentations.
- Calculation of SDG-ONU indicators.

## Risk and Control Analyst.

- Data analysis for operational risk assessment.
- Implementation of statistical models for the measurement of operational risk.
- Tools programming to gather information.
- Systematization of information.
- Generation of Indicators.

## Fellow in the Risk and Control Division.

- Homogenization of the operational risk incident matrix.
- Cost-benefit analysis of values transfer insurance.